Finding Aid for First United Methodist Church of Ypsilanti (Ypsilanti, Mich.) records, 1831-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
First United Methodist Church of Ypsilanti (Ypsilanti, Mich.) records 1831-1995
First United Methodist Church of Ypsilanti (Ypsilanti, Mich.)
1 oversize folders
1 oversize volumes
5 linear feet
86798 Ba 2; UBAm
Methodist Church established in Ypsilanti, Michigan in 1825; church record books; records of Official Board and Quarterly Conferences; minutes and other materials of women’s groups; and subject files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were deposited by the church (donor no. 2412 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The church traces its beginnings to a small group of individuals gathering to listen to an itinerant Methodist preacher in Woodruff's Grove (what would become Ypsilanti) in 1825.
The record group has been arranged into the following series: Church records including lists of members and record of baptisms and marriages; Governance files, including Official Board minutes and Quarterly Conference reports; and records of church groups, especially Ladies Aid, Women's Society of Christian Service, and the Women's Foreign Missionary Society.
Subjects:
First United Methodist Church of Ypsilanti (Ypsilanti, Mich.); United Methodist Church (U.S.)--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Women--Michigan--Ypsilanti--Societies and clubs.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Church history.; Women--Religious life--Michigan--Ypsilanti.
Subjects: Visual Materials
Churches--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; First United Methodist Church of Ypsilanti (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Methodist churches--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Churches.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Church record books
  - Register of baptisms, marriages, membership 1858-1866 (Volume 1)
  - Record book containing revised list of members to 1907 (Box 1)
- Governance
  - Official Board minutes and other records
    - 1831-1834 (Box 1)
    - 1903-1906 (Box 1)
    - 1906-1909 (Box 1)
    - 1916-1920 (Box 1)
    - 1945-1947 (Box 1)
    - 1947-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees minute book 1865-1911 (Box 1)
  - Quarterly Conference record books
    - 1847-1881 (Box 1)
    - 1881-1884 (Box 1)
    - 1884-1889 (Box 1)
    - 1889-1893 (Box 1)
    - 1893-1897 (Box 1)
    - 1897-1901 (Box 1)
    - 1902-1905 (Box 1)
    - 1905-1909 (Box 1)
- Church Groups
  - Ladies' Aid organization
    - Record book 1864-1940
      - 1864-1870 (Box 2)
      - 1870-1880 (Box 2)
      - 1880-1885 (Box 2)
      - 1894-1902 (Box 2)
      - 1906-1912 (Box 2)
      - 1912-1916 (Box 2)
      - 1916-1922 (Box 2)
      - 1922-1932 (Box 2)
      - 1932-1940 (Box 2)
    - Directory (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Women's Home Missionary Society
    - Record book 1928-1937 (Box 2)
    - Annual report, undated, and list of members (Box 2)
  - Women's Society of Christian Service
    - Record book 1935-1949
      - 1935-1940 (Box 2)
      - 1940-1943 (Box 2)
      - 1943-1944 (Box 2)
      - 1944-1945 (Box 3)
      - 1948-1949 (Box 3)
    - Audit 1943-1944 (Box 3)
    - Reports and memoranda 1945-1947 (Box 3)
    - Treasurer's records 1938-1939 (Box 3)
    - Record and Report books 1941-1956, 11 folders (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook of activities 1940-1941 (Box 3)
    - Minutes and other records 1968-1980 (Box 3)
      (the name of the organization was changed to United Methodist Women in the 1970s)
    - Minutes and other records 1981-1989 (Box 4)
    - Treasurer's book 1963-1977 (Box 4)
    - Unit Board meeting minutes (Box 4)
    - Executive board 1990-1995 (Box 4)
  - Women's Foreign Missionary Society
    - Secretary's records 1885-1940
      - 1885-1892 (Box 4)
      - 1892-1902 (Box 4)
      - 1902-1908 (Box 4)
      - 1922-1930 (Box 4)
      - 1930-1935 (Box 4)
      - 1935-1938 (Box 4)
      - 1938-1940 (Box 4)
    - Treasurer's records 1885-1938
      - 1885-1902 (Box 4)
      - 1907-1916 (Box 4)
      - 1916-1925 (Box 4)
      - 1925-1938 (Box 4)
  - King's Guards record book 1922-1924 (Box 4)
  - Circle 5 Record book 1940-1945 (Box 5)
  - Women's Missionary Federation
    - Records 1933-1951 (Box 5)
      - 1933-1940 (Box 5)
      - 1941-1951 (Box 5)
- Other records
  - Subscription list 1836 (Box 5)
  - Warranty deed for church site 1871 (Box 5)
  - Church bulletins 1938-1939 church budgets, 1939-1940, 1940-1941 (Box 5)
  - Donors to church cross (Box 5)
  - Sunday School membership lists, undated; and membership list of "Legion of Methodist Men" (Box 5)
  - Records 1952 of Church Building Survey Committee (Box 5)
  - Church membership transferals 1939-1942 and census report, 1936 (Box 5)
  - Official board members 1938-1939, 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - Pew assignments and rentals 1843-1868, undated (Box 5)
  - "History of Ypsilanti Methodism" by D. L. Davis (Box 5)
  - Biographical sketch of Rev. Charles T. Allen by Frederick E. Quigley (Box 5)
  - Miscellanea (Box 5)
  - Treasurer's book 1864-1867 (Box 5)
  - Notebook of Order of Worship programs 1935-1938 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook- History (Box 5)
  - Audit report 1939 (Box 5)
  - Pageants, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - History of the educational unit (Box 5)
  - Record of the 135th anniversary dinner (Box 5)
  - Directory and miscellanea (Box 5)
  - Duplicates of materials placed in cornerstone 1993 (Box 5)
  - Cassette tape recording of sesquicentennial celebration October 1975 (Box 5)
  - Photographs: Exterior photo of building and interior photo showing renovation; also photographs of church groups (Box 5)
    (see also oversize folder UBAm)